

Katarina.Stuart@auckland.ac nz | +64273556008

Google Scholar Website GitHub

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My interests are in evolutionary genomics and exploring the proximate mechanisms that facilitate local adaptation. Most of my research is conducted on introduced species, as successful invasives provide an important opportunity to observe rapid evolution within a species as it responds to a new ecosystem. Understanding rapid adaptation within invasive populations has applications in many scientific fields, including but not limited to pest control, conservation, organism response to climate change, and evolutionary mechanisms. Many of my projects focus on the invasive starling population in Australia and identifying adaptive genetic shifts post invasion.

My projects and interests cover a range of fields, including genomics, bioinformatics, ecological statistics, and field ecology

EDUCATION

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY (BIOLOGY)

2018-2022

University of New South Wales

Thesis Title: A genetic perspective on rapid adaptation in the globally invasive European

starling (Sturnus vulgaris)

Supervisors: Lee A Rollins, Richard J Edwards, & William B Sherwin

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE (ADVANCED) (HONOURS)

2013-2017

University of Sydney

Thesis Title: Mechanisms generating geographic divergence in phenotypic traits within

the invasive cane toad in Australia

Supervisors: Richard Shine & Gregory Brown

PROFESSIONAL APPOINTMENTS

Research Fellow May 2022 - Present

University of Auckland

Research Assistant 2020-2022

University of New South Wales

Research Assistant August 2017

Deakin University

GRANTS, SCHOLARSHIPS, & AWARDS

SCHOLARSHIPS & RESEARCH GRANTS

2022	GSA Workshop Support Program	1,000 AUD
2022	AES ECR Networking Grant	2,000 AUD
2022	UNSW Science PhD Writing Scholarship	7,500 AUD
2019;2020	Holsworth Wildlife Research Endowment	6,375;7,500 AUD
2018-2022	Australian Government Research Training Program Scholarship	≈27,000 AUD PA

AWARDS

2022 Dean's Award for Outstanding PhD Theses

2022 2021 2021 2020 2019 2018 2018	SMBE Invasomics Conference Oral Presentation Award GSA 2021 Mayo Prize for best student presentation Outstanding E&ERC Postgraduate Researcher Australasian Evolution society student talk award (2 nd Place) The Outstanding Evolution and Ecology Presentation EERC talk COMBINE 2018 Symposium 3 rd place best oral presentation The Outstanding Evolution and Ecology Presentation EERC (2 nd place)	250 NZD - - 200 AUD 200 AUD 50 AUD
TRAVEL GRA	NTS	
2022	School of Biological Science support scheme	1,500 NZD
2022	SMBE Invasomics Conference	400 NZD
2022	University of Auckland FoS Research Fellow Society	500 NZD
2021	Postgraduate Research Student Support (PRSS) Scheme	1,000 AUD
2020	Genetic Society of Australia Smith-White Travel award	-
2018	ABACBS National Conference CSL travel award	200 AUD

PUBLICATIONS

PREPRINT & UNDER REVIEW/REVISION

- 14. Miller SM, <u>Stuart KS</u>, Burke NW, Rollins LA, Bonduriansky R (2022) Genetic and phenotypic consequences of local transitions between sexual and parthenogenetic reproduction in the wild. *BioRXIV*, https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.11.02.514965
- 13. Ahrens C, Chen S, Bothwell H, <u>Stuart KC</u>, Edwards RJ, Bragg J (2022) A genome-wide view of adaptation across the landscape. *New Phytologist*, under Review.
- 12. Li-Williams S[†], Stuart KC[†], Comte S, Forsyth DM, Dawson M, Sherwin WB, Rollins LA. (2022) Population genetic analyses clarify invasive rusa deer movement across peri-urban environments, Wildlife Research, under review. († indicates joint first authorship)
- 11. Hofmeister NR, Stuart KC, Warren WC, Werner SJ, Bateson M, Ball GF, Buchanan KL, Burt DW, Cardilini APA, Cassey P, De Meyer T, George J, Meddle SL, Rowland HM, Sherman CDH, Sherwin WB, Berghe WV, Rollins LA, Clayton DF (2021). Concurrent invasions by European starlings (Sturnus vulgaris) suggest selection on shared genomic regions even after genetic bottlenecks. BioRXIV, https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.19.442026
- 10. Zhou J, Nelson TM, Lopez CR, Zhou SJ, Ward-Fear G, <u>Stuart KC</u>, Rollins LA (2021) Microbial function is related to behavior of an invasive anuran. *BioRXIV*, https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.11.16.385690

PEER REVIEWED ARTICLES

-2023-

- 9. <u>Stuart KC</u>, Edwards, RJ, Sherwin WB, Rollins, LA. (2023) Contrasting patterns of single nucleotide polymorphisms and structural variations across multiple invasions. *Molecular Biology and Evolution*, 40(3): msad046. https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msad046
- 8. <u>Stuart KC</u>[†], Hofmeister NR[†], Zichello JM, Rollins LA. (2023) Global invasion history and native decline of the common starling, *Biological Invasions*. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10530-022-02982-5 († joint first author)
- 7. <u>Stuart KC</u>, Sherwin WB, Edwards RJ*, Rollins LA* (2023) Evolution, genomics, and the globally invasive European starling, *Frontiers in Genetics* (* indicates joint last authorship). https://doi.org/10.3389/fgene.2022.1010456

-2022-

- 6. <u>Stuart KC</u>[†], Edwards RJ[†], Cheng Y, Warren WC, Burt DW, Sherwin WB, Hofmeister NR, Werner SJ, Ball GF, Bateson M, Brandley MC, Buchanan KL, Cassey P, Clayton DF, De Meyer T, Meddle SL, Rollins LA (2021). Transcript- and annotation-guided genome assembly of the European starling. *Molecular Ecology Resources*, https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.07.438753 † joint first author
- 5. <u>Stuart KC</u>, Sherwin WB, Cardilini APA, Rollins LA (2022). Genetics and plasticity are responsible for climate induced ecogeographical patterns in a recent invasion. *Frontiers in Genetics* DOI: https://doi.org/10.3389/fgene.2022.824424.
- 4. <u>Stuart KC</u>, Sherwin WB, Austin JJ, Bateson M, Eens M, Brandley MC, Rollins LA (2022). Historical museum samples enable the examination of divergent and parallel evolution during invasion. *Molecular Ecology*, 31(6):1836-1852, https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.16353.

-2021-

3. <u>Stuart KC</u>[†], Cardilini APA[†], Cassey P, Richardson MF, Sherwin W, Rollins LA^{*}, Sherman CDH^{*}. (2021) Signatures of selection in a recent invasion reveal adaptive divergence in a highly vagile invasive species. *Molecular Ecology*, 30(6):1419-1434, https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.15601 († indicates joint first authorship, *indicates joint last authorship)

Featured in Molecular Ecology News and Views: https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.15794

-2019-

2. <u>Stuart KC</u>, Brown GP, Shine R. (2019) Proximate mechanisms underlying the rapid modification of phenotypic traits in cane toads (*Rhinella marina*) across their invasive range within Australia. *Biol J Linnean Soc.* 126(1):68-79, https://doi.org/10.1093/biolinnean/bly150

-2018-

1. Hudson CM, Brown GP, <u>Stuart KC</u>, Shine R. (2018) Sexual and geographical divergence in head widths of invasive cane toads, *Rhinella marina* (Anura: Bufonidae), is driven by both rapid evolution and plasticity. *Biol J Linnean Soc.* 124(2):188-99, https://doi.org/10.1093/biolinnean/bly040

PEER REVIEWED BOOK CHATPERS

1. <u>Stuart KC</u>, Woolnough AP, Rollins LA. (2023) Invasive species detection and management using genomic methods. in Holleley, C.E., Berry, O. and Jarman, S. Applied Ecological Genetics. CSIRO Publishing, Canberra

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2018- BABS3291 - Genes, Genomes and Evolution

UNSW Sydney, AUS

Laboratory demonstrator for a third-year biotechnology and biomolecular sciences subject, teaching students with a range of biological and coding knowledge. Key topics include introduction to evolutionary bioinformatics, fundamental genomic principles, and investigation into recent advancements in the field.

2021 BIOC2201 - Principles of molecular biology

UNSW Sydney, AUS

Laboratory demonstrator and tutor for a second-year biochemistry subject, with key topics including an introduction to modern molecular biology, molecular mechanisms of gene expression, and fundamental aspects of recombinant DNA technology

2019- BABS2204 - Genetics

UNSW Sydney, AUS

Laboratory demonstrator for a second-year biotechnology and biomolecular sciences subject. Duties include supervising classes to ensure safely protocols are adhered to, marking assignments, and supervising assessable tasks. I was responsible for motivating constructive discussion among students, as well as explaining biological processed to students, and assisting with experimental procedures.

2021 BIOC2101 - Principles of Biochemistry

UNSW Sydney, AUS

Laboratory demonstrator for a second-year biochemistry subject, with key topics including and introduction to modern biochemistry, and covers fundamental aspects of the structure-function relationships of proteins and an overall coverage of intermediary metabolism.

2020 Science and Engineering Indigenous Preparatory Program Project Developer and Instructor for the Science and Engineering Indigenous Preparatory Program. Prepared and delivered 3 hours of first year university level biology teaching content for incoming and prospective first year university students.

2019 ANGUS 2019 - Data Intensive Biology Summer Institute UC Davis, USA Teaching assistant at the ANGUS summer course held through the Data Intensive Biology Summer Institute and the Lab for Data Intensive Biology at UC Davis. Taught learners from varied backgrounds (undergraduate to professorial) genomic practices for analysing big shotgun sequencing data sets over the intensive two-week course, as well as working one on one with learners on their own data sets.

Supervision Experience

2021- Masters student supervision

2022 Project involved reduced representation sequencing of invasive deer in conjunction with the NSW Department of Primary Industries.

2019 NSW Year 12 Extension Science Project Supervisor

Primary supervisor for final high school year student on an extension science project. Work covered developing coding, analytical, writing, and general scientific skills to help them produce a report in fulfillment of their course outcomes. Assisted student in preparing a conference presentation, which they gave at the 2019 Australasian Evolution Conference.

SCIENTIFIC PRESENTATIONS

INVITE	D TALKS	
2023	Sydney Bioinformatics Seminar Series A whole genome perspective on genetic variation and rapid adaptation	Virtual
2021	Queensland Technologies and Innovations group seminar talk The draft genome assembly of the globally invasive common starling, Sturnus vulgaris	Virtual
2020	Genetics Society of AustralAsia Award Symposium Whole transcripts in genome assembly, annotation, and assessment: the draft genome assembly of the globally invasive common starling, Sturnus vulgaris	Virtual
TALKS		
2022	Australasian Evolution Society National Conference Genetics and plasticity are responsible for ecogeographical patterns in a recent invasion.	ANU, AUS
2022	NZ Molecular Ecology Conference Contrasting patterns of single nucleotide polymorphisms and structural variations across multiple invasions.	NZ
2022	SMBE Invasomics Conference Contrasting patterns of single nucleotide polymorphisms and structural variations across multiple invasions.	UoW, NZ
2022	ComBio/Genetics Society of Australasia Genetics and plasticity are responsible for ecogeographical patterns in a recent invasion.	UoM, AUS

2021	Australasian Evolution Society Conference A genetic perspective on rapid adaptation in the globally invasive European starling (Sturnus vulgaris).	Virtual
2021	Genetics Society of AustralAsia Conference A genetic perspective on rapid adaptation in the globally invasive European starling (Sturnus vulgaris).	Virtual
2020	Australasian Evolution Society Conference Rapid Adaptation in invasive species: Using historical museum samples to examine evolution in an invasive passerine.	Virtual
2020	Postgraduate Research Form Investigating evolution using invasive species and historical museum samples.	Virtual
2020	ABACBS Virtual Conference Whole transcripts in genome assembly, annotation, and assessment: the draft genome assembly of the globally invasive common starling, Sturnus vulgaris.	Virtual
2019	Postgraduate Research Form Evolution in invasive species: exploring adaptive divergence and selection across the Australian landscape.	UNSW, AUS
2019	Australasian Evolution Society National Conference Local signatures of founding populations confound identification of adaptive divergence in invasive populations.	UNSW, AUS
2018	COMBINE Symposium Evolution in invasive populations: using genomics to reveal drivers of invasion success in the Australian European starling (Sturnus vulgaris) introduction across Australia.	UM, AUS
2018	Postgraduate Research Form, University of New South Wales Evolution in invasive populations: using genomics to reveal drivers of invasion success in the Australian European starling (Sturnus vulgaris) introduction across space and time.	UNSW, AUS
POSTE	RS	
2022	Lorne Genome Conference A genetic perspective on rapid adaptation in the globally invasive European starling (Sturnus vulgaris).	Lorne, AUS
2019	GIW/ABACBS International Conference Using genomics to reveal drivers of invasion success.	USYD, AUS
2019	COMBINE/AYRCOB Symposium Using genomics to reveal drivers of invasion success.	USYD, AUS
2018	ABACBS National Conference Evolution in invasive populations: using genomics to reveal drivers of invasion success in the Australian European starling (Sturnus vulgaris) introduction across Australia.	UM, AUS

SERVICE & OUTREACH

SERVICE

- 2023 Centre for Computational Evolution seminar series organiser
- 2023 International Congress of Genetics conference 2023 Symposia Organiser
- 2021 **GSA 2021 Virtual Conference Committee** *Committee Member*Assisted with the organisation of the 2021 Genetics Society of AustralAsia Virtual Conference.
- 2018- Sydney Society for Conservation Biology President, Communications

- Responsible for managing the society board committee, overseeing finances and event organisation and execution. Additionally, responsible for maintaining the social media pages (Facebook and Twitter), and organised and wrote a monthly newsletter for society members.
- 2019 COMBINE General Committee Symposium Coordinator
 I was responsible for assembling the 2019 COMBINE symposium committee, supervising the organisation of all aspects of the event. Key roles include meeting outcome deadlines, ensuring budget restraints were met and invoiced, and assisting to organise the assembly of a guest careers panels.
- 2019- E&ERC Postgraduate Committee Committee Member
- My job is to provide a lively, inclusive, fun and academically enriching experience for all postgraduates in the E&ERC. I organise formal and informal centre gatherings, two seminar speakers, encourage student participation in centre activities and help integrate new students.
- 2019 GIW/ABACBS 2019 Conference Committee COMBINE representative
 Liaised between the ABACBS conference committee and COMBINE symposium committee to ensure budget and time restraints were met.
- 2019 **AES 2019 Conference Committee** *Committee Member*Assisted with the organisation of the 2019 Australasian Evolution Society Conference.

OUTREACH

- 2020, Boiling Point Science Podcast Guest
- 2022 Guest on EastSide 89.7 FM science podcast Boiling Point (August 2020, May 2022)
- 2014- Australian National Museum Volunteer
- Assisting with running events and demonstration, chaperoning school groups, and general communications and operational duties during Australian Science Week.
- 2016 Friends of Fogg Dam Invited Speaker
 Gave a talk to a community ecology and restoration group on the developing aspects of my honours research.

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT & TRAINING

2022	Carpentries Instructor Training and Certification	University of Auckland, NZ
2020	UNSW Women in Maths and Science Champions Program	UNSW Sydney, AUS
2020	Sessional Staff Development Program	UNSW Sydney, AUS
2018	Bioconductor Hands-on Training Day 4th Bioconductor Asia meeting	University of Melbourne, AUS
2018	Sample Size and Power Calculations Stats Central	UNSW Sydney, AUS
2018	ANGUS - Analysing Sequencing Data Data Intensive Biology Summer Institute	UC Davis, USA
2018	Software Carpentry Workshop - R, Unix shell, Git	Curtin University, AUS

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIP

2022- Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution (SMBE)

2020-	Genetics Society of AustralAsia (GSA)
2019-	AustralAsian Evolution Society (AES)
2018- 2021	Australian Bioinformatics and Computational Biology Society (ABACBS)
2018- 2021	Ecological Society of Australia (ESA)

REFERENCES

Associate Professor Lee Ann Rollins Scientia Fellow School of Biological, Earth and Environmental Sciences, University of New South Wales, Sydney NSW 2052 Professor Richard Shine Professor School of Natural Sciences, Macquarie University, North Ryde NSW 2109	l.rollins@unsw.edu.au +61 9385 6316 rick.shine@mq.edu.au
Dr Gregory Brown Post-Doc	greg.brown@mq.edu.au
School of Natural Sciences, Macquarie University, North Ryde NSW 2109	08 8984 9137